{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following teachings was given to people by Rishabhnath before starting of an Era?",
            "optionA": "  Krishi ",
            "optionB": "  Masi ",
            "optionC": "  Asi ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishi, Masi, Asi teachings was given to people by Rishabhnath. ",
            "keyString": "394847s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddha attained nirvana at __________",
            "optionA": "  Bodh Gaya ",
            "optionB": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionC": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionD": "  Kusinagara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBodh Gaya in the Gaya district, in the state of Bihar, was where Gautama Buddha attained Nirvana. ",
            "keyString": "394885s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After which Tirthankar, Sambhavanath Tirthankar was born?",
            "optionA": "  Rishabnath ",
            "optionB": "  Ajitnath ",
            "optionC": "  Abhinandan ",
            "optionD": "  Padyaprabhu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjitnathTirthankar was born before Sambhavanath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "394901s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the symbol of Sambhavanatha Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Elephant ",
            "optionB": "  Cow ",
            "optionC": "  Horse ",
            "optionD": "  Tortoise ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSambhavanatha was the third Jain tirthankara (omniscient teaching god) of the present age. Sambavanatha is associated with Horse emblem, Sala tree, Trimukha (three-faced) Yaksha and Prajnapthi & Duritari Yakshi.",
            "keyString": "394915s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Indo-Greek Kin, who embraced Buddhism was __________",
            "optionA": "  Strato I ",
            "optionB": "  Menander ",
            "optionC": "  Demetrios ",
            "optionD": "  Alexander ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMenander I Soter was an Indo-Greek King of the Indo-Greek Kingdom who administered a large empire in the Northwestern regions of the Indian Subcontinent from his capital at Sagala. Menander is noted for having become a patron of Buddhism. Menander was initially a king of Bactria. ",
            "keyString": "394927s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The worship of images (of Buddha) in India began during the period",
            "optionA": "  Mauryan ",
            "optionB": "  Sunga ",
            "optionC": "  Kushana ",
            "optionD": "  Gupta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kushan Empire was a syncretic empire, formed by the Yuezhi, in the Bactrian territories in the early 1st century. It spread to encompass much of Afghanistan, and then the northern parts of the Indian subcontinent at least as far as Saketa and Sarnath near Varanasi (Benares), where inscriptions have been found dating to the era of the Kushan Emperor Kanishka the Great. Emperor Kanishka was a great patron of Buddhism. He played an important role in the establishment of Buddhism in the Indian subcontinent and its spread to Central Asia and China. ",
            "keyString": "435810s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Gandhar of Sumtinath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Bhanuraj ",
            "optionB": "  Vishwasen ",
            "optionC": "  Kritverma ",
            "optionD": "  Charam Swami ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharam Swami was the first Gandhar of Sumtinath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "435932s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the Kalinga War, Ashoka decided never to wage any war because?",
            "optionA": "  After the conquest of Kalinga the political unity of Mauryan India had been achieved ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka felt apologetic about the destruction of men and material on both sides in the war ",
            "optionC": "  He was moved by the violence, slaughter and sufferings to the combatants and noncombatants in the war ",
            "optionD": "  Shortly after the war he adopted Buddhism which was opposed to violence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka was an Indian Emperor of the Maurya Dynasty , who ruled almost all of the Indian subcontinent from\u2009268 to 232 BCE.The Kalinga war, the sight of such a carnage and massacre of human lives, and the sufferings of the wounde made a deep impression on Ashoka's mind. The unhappiness of the women and children made him very sad and unhappy .He vowed never to make a war again in his life. He decided to devote the rest of his life to the spread of Dharma. Thus the Kalinga war became a turning point of his life. ",
            "keyString": "436022s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka has been particularly influenced by the Buddhist monk",
            "optionA": "  Ambhi ",
            "optionB": "  Upagupta ",
            "optionC": "  Asvaghosha ",
            "optionD": "  Vasubandhu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUpagupta (c. 3rd Century BC) was a Buddhist monk. According to some stories in the Sanskrit text Ashokavadana, he was the spiritual teacher of the Mauryan emperor Ashoka. Upagupta's teacher was Sanavasi who was a disciple of Ananda, the Buddha's attendant. Due to the absence of his name in Theravada literature, it is assumed that Upagupta was a Sarvastivadin monk. ",
            "keyString": "436085s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a sect of Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Mahayana ",
            "optionB": "  Hinayana ",
            "optionC": "  Digambar ",
            "optionD": "  Theravad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDigambara (\"sky-clad\") is one of the two major schools of Jainism, the other being Svetambara (white-clad). The word Digambara (Sanskrit) is a combination of two words: dig (directions) and ambara (sky), referring to those whose garments are of the element that fills the four quarters of space. Mahayana, Hinayana, Theravad are the parts of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "436137s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chinese travellers visited India primarily because-",
            "optionA": "  They were interested in Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  They were invited by ten Indian kings ",
            "optionC": "  They were interested to study Indian culture ",
            "optionD": "  They were interested to stay in India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAncient India there were two greatest Chinese visitor Faxian and Xuanzang. Faxian is known as Fa hein, he came to India in the beginning of 5th century A.D. He was the first chinese monk who visited India. He was a Chinese Buddhist monk, pilgrim traveller and writer, author of one of the earliest and most valuable Chinese accounts of India. He came India to Visit Buddhist place and to collect sacred work connected with the life and the teachings of the Buddha. He entered India from North West and reached patliputra. Fa hein visit India in the period of Chandragupta II. ",
            "keyString": "485004s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddhism was first propagated outside India In",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Cambodia ",
            "optionC": "  Thailand ",
            "optionD": "  Ceylon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddhism was first propagated outside India In ceylon. ",
            "keyString": "485037s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The early Buddhist scriptures were composed in",
            "optionA": "  Prakrit texts ",
            "optionB": "  Pali texts ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit texts ",
            "optionD": "  Pictographical texts ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sacred book of Buddhism is called the Tripitaka (called Tipitaka in Pali). It is also called the Pali Canon, after the language in which it was first written. ",
            "keyString": "485051s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Nakshatra (constellation) Sumtinath Tirthankar was born?",
            "optionA": "  Satbhisha Nakshatra ",
            "optionB": "  Dhanishtha ",
            "optionC": "  Shravan ",
            "optionD": "  Magha Nakshtra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSumatinatha was born to Kshatriya King Megha (Meghaprabha) and Queen Mangala (Sumangala) at Ayodhya in the Ikshvaku dynasty. His birth date was the eighth day of the Vaisakha Sudi Magha Nakshtra in month of the Jain calendar. ",
            "keyString": "485062s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Buddhist Council was held at",
            "optionA": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Rajgriha ",
            "optionC": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionD": "  Vaisali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Buddhist Council: 400 BC. Held soon after the mahaparinirvana of the Buddha, around 400 BC under the patronage of king Ajatshatru with the monk Mahakasyapa presiding, at Rajgriha, in the Sattapani Cave. The idea was to preserve Buddha's teachings (Sutta) and rules for disciples (Vinaya). ",
            "keyString": "485073s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of following Buddhist councils compilation of holy books was completed?",
            "optionA": "  Rajgir ",
            "optionB": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Vaishali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the scriptures of all Buddhist schools, the first Buddhist Council was held soon after the death of the Buddha, dated by the majority of recent scholars around 400 BCE, under the patronage of the king Ajatashatru with the monk Mahakasyapa presiding, at Sattapanni caves Rajgriha (now Rajgir). ",
            "keyString": "534179s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the patron of the 3rd Buddhist council?",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Harsha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Third Buddhist council was convened in about 250 BCE at Asokarama in Pataliputra, supposedly under the patronage of Emperor Ashoka. The council recommended the ruler Ashoka to expel sixty thousand brahmanic spies as well as reevaluate the P\u0101li Canon. ",
            "keyString": "534217s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddha has been described as 'an ocean of wisdom and compassion' In",
            "optionA": "  The Light of Asia ",
            "optionB": "  Amarakosa ",
            "optionC": "  Buddhacharita ",
            "optionD": "  Jatak Tales ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddha has been described as 'an ocean of wisdom and compassion' in Amarakosa. The fifth and sixth verses give various names of Gautama Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "534235s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which script were the Ashokan inscription were written in North West Frontier Province?",
            "optionA": "  Prakrit ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmi ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Kharoshti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Kharoshti script, the Ashokan inscription were written in North West Frontier Province. ",
            "keyString": "534249s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Jain Shastra, Manno Sahssisso Bhimo, __________",
            "optionA": "  Sidha ",
            "optionB": "  A Si Sahu ",
            "optionC": "  Namorhastiadheybahhy ",
            "optionD": "  Durtthasso Paridhawad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Jainas, the world is composed of two different kinds of substances, the Jiva (conscious) and the ajiva (unconscious). These are the uncreated existing constituents of the Universe which impart the necessary dynamics to the Universe by interacting with each other. These constituents behave according to the natural laws and their nature without interference from external entities. Dharma or true religion according to Jainism is Vatthu sahavo dhammo translated as \"the intrinsic nature of a substance is its true dharma.\" ",
            "keyString": "534261s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is the sacred book of the Buddhists?",
            "optionA": "  Upanishad ",
            "optionB": "  Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Tripitaka ",
            "optionD": "  Jatakas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tripitaka (Pali Canon), Mahayana Sutras and the Tibetan Book of the Dead are three major noncanonical Buddhist texts. The Pali Canon, which means \"the word of Buddha,\" includes some of the Buddha's discourse, but it also incorporates the teachings of his pupils. ",
            "keyString": "588030s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tirthankar Ajitnath was detached from whose effects?",
            "optionA": "  Padprabhu ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya Aridaman ",
            "optionC": "  Arahnath ",
            "optionD": "  Naminath ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTirthankar Ajitnath was detached from Acharya Aridaman effects. ",
            "keyString": "588066s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the cause of the decline of Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism was founded by a prince ",
            "optionB": "  Corruption crept into Buddhist monasteries ",
            "optionC": "  Buddha and Mahavira were contemporaries ",
            "optionD": "  Buddha preached non-violence ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe important cause of the decline and fall of Buddhism was the decline of Buddhist Sanghas. The Sanghas became centres of corruption. The discipline of vinay pitaka was violated. The viharas were dominated by ease-loving people. The monks and nuns began to lead lives of pleasure and ease. The Mahayanist and Hinayanist quarreled with each other. Internal conflict proved to be the ruin of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "588083s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During whose reign did Buddhism become the state religion?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Skandagupta I ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka's personal religion became Buddhism, if not before, then certainly after the Kalinga war. Nevertheless, his patronage led to the expansion of Buddhism in the Mauryan empire and other kingdoms during his rule, and worldwide from about 250 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "588098s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The word Jina from which the Jain(ism) has originated stands for",
            "optionA": "  great ",
            "optionB": "  detached ",
            "optionC": "  non-violence ",
            "optionD": "  conqueror (of senses) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jainism, a word derived from the Sanskrit word jina (victor) and connoting the path of victory in crossing over life's stream of rebirths through an ethical and spiritual life. ",
            "keyString": "588110s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During young age, what did Sambhavnath Tirthankar feel while watching the dispersal of medieval clouds?",
            "optionA": "  Togetherness ",
            "optionB": "  Mortification ",
            "optionC": "  Happy ",
            "optionD": "  Sad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSambhavnath Tirthankar felt mortifcation while watching the dispersal of medieval clouds. ",
            "keyString": "635161s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Buddhist elements \nII. Secular aspects \nIII. Jain culture\nWhich of the above statements is/are correct related to Ajanta Painting portray ?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionD": "  Only III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five elements are Earth, Water, Fire, Wind, and Void. ",
            "keyString": "635199s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Jataka tales?\nI. It is a collection of tales belonging to the pre-Buddhist period give us a revealing glimpse into a period when the fusion between the Aryan and the Dravidian races had been almost completed.\nII. It gives us the periods of rule and genealogies of dynasties of kings.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJataka tales is a collection of tales belonging to the pre-Buddhist period give us a revealing glimpse into a period when the fusion between the Aryan and the Dravidian races had been almost completed. It gives us the periods of rule and genealogies of dynasties of kings. ",
            "keyString": "635219s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest Kushana ruler whose contribution to Buddhism was even greater than that of Ashoka, was",
            "optionA": "  Kadphises ",
            "optionB": "  Kanishka I ",
            "optionC": "  Vasishka ",
            "optionD": "  Huvishka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka, A descendant of Kujula Kadphises - founder of the Kushan empire - Kanishka came to rule an empire in Bactria extending from Turfan in the Tarim Basin to Pataliputra on the Gangetic plain. The main capital of his empire was located at Puru\u1e63apura in Gandhara, with another major capital at Kapisa. He was the greatest Kushana ruler whose contribution to Buddhism was even greater than that of Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "635235s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the first discourse that the Buddha had delivered at the Deer Park in Sarnath called?",
            "optionA": "  Mahaparinirvana ",
            "optionB": "  Mahamastabhisheka ",
            "optionC": "  Mahabhiniskraman ",
            "optionD": "  Dharmachakrapravartan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sermon, Buddha gave to the five monks, was his first sermon, called the Dharmachakrapravartan. It was given on the full-moon day of Asalha Puja. Buddha subsequently also spent his first rainy season at Sarnath at the Mulagandhakuti. ",
            "keyString": "635248s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ajitnath Tirthankar was born on the eighth day of which Hindu month of shukl paksh?",
            "optionA": "  Maagh ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitra ",
            "optionC": "  Ashwin ",
            "optionD": "  Jyestha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe queen gave birth to a son on the eighth day of the bright half of the month of Magh. Inspired by the popular lore, the king named the new born as the Ajit. ",
            "keyString": "691915s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The language adopted for preaching In Mahayana Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Pali ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmi ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Prakrit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahayana is one of two main existing branches of Buddhism and a term for classification of Buddhist philosophies and practice. They adopted Sanskrit language. ",
            "keyString": "691979s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The proceedings of the Third Buddhist Council led to the issue of Edict?",
            "optionA": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionB": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionC": "  Bhabra ",
            "optionD": "  Kalinga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe proceedings of the Third Buddhist Council led to the issue of Sarnath Edict. ",
            "keyString": "692000s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not included in triratna of Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  Right Knowledge ",
            "optionB": "  Right Conduct ",
            "optionC": "  Right Faith ",
            "optionD": "  Creator ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCreator is not included in triratna of Jainism. ",
            "keyString": "692016s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Minor Rock Edicts of Ashoka describes the Conquest of Kalinga by Ashoka?",
            "optionA": "  No. XIII ",
            "optionB": "  No. X ",
            "optionC": "  No. XI ",
            "optionD": "  No. XII ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinor Rock Edicts of Ashoka describes the Conquest of Kalinga by Ashoka in rock Edict XIII. ",
            "keyString": "692031s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the Kushana ruler patronised Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Vikramaditya ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Kautilya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka patronised Buddhism that played an important role in the development of the Silk Road, and in the transmission of Mahayana Buddhism from Gandhara across the Karakoram range to China. ",
            "keyString": "739521s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which descent Abhinandannath Tirthankar was born?",
            "optionA": "  Ikswakshu Vansh ",
            "optionB": "  Nand Vansh ",
            "optionC": "  Gulam Vansh ",
            "optionD": "  Duguwa Vansh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinandannatha or Abhinandan Swami was the fourth Tirthankara of the present age (Avasarpini). Abhinandanan\u0101tha is said to have lived for 50 lakh purva. Abhinandannath was born to King Sanvara Raja and Queen Sidharta Rani at Ayodhya in the Ikshvaku clan. His birth date was the second day of the Magh shukla month of the Indian calendar. According to Jain beliefs, he became a siddha, a liberated soul which has destroyed all of its Karma. ",
            "keyString": "739558s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Nakshatra (constellation) Abhinandannath Tirthankar was born?",
            "optionA": "  Satbhisha Nakshatra ",
            "optionB": "  Dhanishtha ",
            "optionC": "  Shravan ",
            "optionD": "  Punarvasu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Punarvasu Nakshatra (constellation) Abhinandannath Tirthankar was born. The word Punarvasu is derived from Puna + Vasu, which means return, renewal, restoration or repetition. The 12 Adityas were born of Kasyapa in the womb of Aditi. ",
            "keyString": "739574s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vardhamana Mahavira the 24 th Tirthankar of Jainism was born at __________ and died at __________",
            "optionA": "  Vaishali and Rajagriha ",
            "optionB": "  Kusinara and Pava ",
            "optionC": "  Kundagrama and Pava ",
            "optionD": "  Kashi and Champa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahavira, (Sanskrit: \"Great Hero\") also known as Vardhamana, (born c. 599 bce traditional dating, Kshatriyakundagrama, India\u2014died 527 traditional dating, Pavapuri), Epithet of Vardhamana, the last of the 24 Tirthankaras (\"Ford-makers\", i.e., saviours who promulgated Jainism), and the reformer of the Jain monastic. ",
            "keyString": "739588s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During whose reign did the Gandhara School of Art blossom?",
            "optionA": "  Harsha ",
            "optionB": "  Ashok ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta-II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhara School of Art blossom in the reign of Kanishka. The Gandhara art is basically the result of Hellenistic influences on Buddhism. That is why it is also called Greco-Buddhist art. The reign of a single king cannot be attributed as the cause for the evolution of the art. ",
            "keyString": "739601s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From which monument, Gautama Buddha propagated his divine knowledge of Buddhism to the world?",
            "optionA": "  Humayun's Tomb ",
            "optionB": "  Mahabodhi Temple Complex ",
            "optionC": "  Qutub Minar ",
            "optionD": "  Red Fort Complex ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mahabodhi Temple, a UNESCO World Heritage Site, is an ancient, but much rebuilt and restored, Buddhist temple in Bodh Gaya, marking the location where the Buddha is said to have attained enlightenment. Bodh Gaya is about 96 km from Patna, Bihar state, India. ",
            "keyString": "819897s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are correct statement(s) related to the Buddhist Philosophy?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhist philosophy deals extensively with problems in metaphysics, phenomenology, ethics and epistemology. ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhism is a non-theistic system of beliefs based on the teachings of Siddhartha Gautama, an Indian prince later known as the Buddha, in the 5th Century ",
            "optionC": "",
            "optionD": " ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddhist philosophy refers to the philosophical investigations and systems of inquiry that developed among various Buddhist schools in India following the death of the Buddha and later spread throughout Asia. The Buddhist path combines both philosophical reasoning and meditation. ",
            "keyString": "819932s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indo-Greek king, who became Buddhist?",
            "optionA": "  Antiochus II ",
            "optionB": "  Apollodotus I ",
            "optionC": "  Apollodotus II ",
            "optionD": "  Menander I ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMenander I Soter was an Indo-Greek King of the Indo-Greek Kingdom who administered a large empire in the Northwestern regions of the Indian Subcontinent from his capital at Sagala. Menander is noted for having become a patron of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "819945s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The jainas follow the practice of worshipping images of tirthankaras.\nReason (R): They denied the existence of a Supreme Being.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImmediately after attaining keval jnana, if a person establishes the four fold religious order of monks, nuns, sravaks (male householder), and sravikas (female householder) is known as Tirthankar. He preaches the Jain philosophy, religion, ethics, conducts to his followers. The only difference between Tirthankara and simple kevali is that the latter does not establish the religious order. He remains in the state of perfect blissful condition for the rest of his life after attaining keval gyan. ",
            "keyString": "819958s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Jainism in India?",
            "optionA": "  Gautama ",
            "optionB": "  Mahavira ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Gupta ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJains revere him as the twenty-fourth and last tirthankara of present cosmic age. Though, Mahavira is sometimes mistakenly regarded as the founder, he appears in the tradition as one who, from the beginning, had followed a religion established long ago. ",
            "keyString": "819971s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Three Jewels' (Triratnas) of Jainism are",
            "optionA": "  right faith or intentions, right knowledge and right conduct ",
            "optionB": "  right action, right livelihood and right effort ",
            "optionC": "  right thoughts, non-violence and non-attachment ",
            "optionD": "  right speech, right thinking and right behaviour ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jainism the three jewels (also referred to as ratnatraya) are understood as samyagdarshana (\"right faith\"), samyagjnana (\"right knowledge\"), and samyakcharitra (\"right conduct\"). One of the three cannot exist exclusive of the others, and all are required for spiritual liberation. ",
            "keyString": "888645s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Identify the Buddhist Literature from the following",
            "optionA": "  Tripitakas ",
            "optionB": "  Upanishads ",
            "optionC": "  Angas ",
            "optionD": "  Aranyakas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tripitaka is the traditional term for the Buddhist scriptures. The version canonical to Theravada Buddhism is generally referred to in English as the Pali Canon. Mahayana Buddhism also holds the Tripitaka to be authoritative but, unlike Theravadins, it also includes in its canon various derivative literature and commentaries that were composed much later. ",
            "keyString": "888705s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many Ganadharas were there in the religious family of Sambhavnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  95 ",
            "optionB": "  105 ",
            "optionC": "  115 ",
            "optionD": "  125 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t105 Ganadharas were there in the religious family of Sambhavnath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "889078s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahavira's first disciple was",
            "optionA": "  Bhadrabahu ",
            "optionB": "  Sthulabhadra ",
            "optionC": "  Charvaka ",
            "optionD": "  Jamali ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJamali who was husband of Anonja Priyadarshini, became the first disciple of Mahavira. ",
            "keyString": "889221s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following 'MATH' is related with Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Dakhma ",
            "optionB": "  Chaitya ",
            "optionC": "  Khangah ",
            "optionD": "  Angeri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA chaitya, chaitya hall, chaitya-griha, or caitya refers to a shrine, sanctuary, temple or prayer hall in South Asian religions. The term is most common in Buddhism, where it includes a stupa at one end.",
            "keyString": "889342s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The religious movements of Buddhism and Jainism were led by",
            "optionA": "  Sudras ",
            "optionB": "  Kshatriya Princes ",
            "optionC": "  Vaisyas ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmins ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe religious movements of Buddhism and Jainism were led by Kshatriya Princes. ",
            "keyString": "964200s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the last Buddhist\ntext produced In India?",
            "optionA": "  Divya Vandana ",
            "optionB": "  Dohakosa ",
            "optionC": "  Vjrachedika ",
            "optionD": "  Vamsathapakasini ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVamsathapakasini was the last Buddhist text produced In India. Vamsathapakasini gives us information about the Kshatriya origin of the Mauryas. ",
            "keyString": "964238s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fourth and the last Buddhist Council was convened by",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Menander ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Huvishka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Theravada had a Fourth Buddhist Council in the first century BCE in Tambapanni, Another Fourth Buddhist Council was held in the Sarvastivada tradition, said to have been convened by the Kushan emperor Kanishka, in 78 AD at Kundalban in Kashmir. ",
            "keyString": "964255s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most famous Indo-Greek ruler of India, famous for his sense of Justice and dialogues with a Buddhist monk Nagasena (as described in the Buddhist work Milinda Panho) was",
            "optionA": "  Demetrius ",
            "optionB": "  Menander ",
            "optionC": "  Eukratises ",
            "optionD": "  Heliocles ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMenander was a Greek dramatist and the best-known representative of Athenian New Comedy. He wrote 108 comedies and took the prize at the Lenaia festival eight times. His record at the City Dionysia is unknown but may well have been similarly spectacular. Menander was famous for his sense of Justice and dialogues with a Buddhist monk Nagasena (as described in the Buddhist work Milinda Panho). ",
            "keyString": "964270s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following Mudra is the gesture of Buddha as depicted in his first sermon?",
            "optionA": "  Abhaya Mudra ",
            "optionB": "  Dhyana Mudra ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmachakra Mudra ",
            "optionD": "  Bhumisparsa Mudra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDharmachakra mudra is one of such interesting and unique hand gestures used in Buddha statues which means the wheel of Dharma in Buddhism. The Dharmachakra mudra is also known as gesture of Teaching of the Wheel of Dharma. This gesture depicts one of the most important moment in the Buddha's life as he performed the Dharmachakra mudra in his first sermon in Sarnath after he attained enlightenment. ",
            "keyString": "964283s12m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name Buddha means",
            "optionA": "  enlightened ",
            "optionB": "  learned ",
            "optionC": "  divine ",
            "optionD": "  sacred ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Buddha is one who has attained Bodhi; and by Bodhi is meant wisdom, an ideal state of intellectual and ethical perfection which can be achieved by man through purely human means. The term Buddha literally means enlightened one, a knower. ",
            "keyString": "43726s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following could be associated with Buddhism?\nI. Rejection of the authority of Vedas\nII. Denial of God\nIII. Belief in the categories of jiva and ajiva\nIV. The concept of nirvana\nV. Theory of prakriti and purusha",
            "optionA": "  I,II and III ",
            "optionB": "  II,III,IV and I ",
            "optionC": "  I,II and IV ",
            "optionD": "  I,III,IV and V ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Rejection of the authority of Vedas, Denial of God, The concept of nirvana is related with Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "44002s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following place, Buddha was never depicted in a human form but was represented only as a symbol of either two footprints or wheel?",
            "optionA": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionB": "  Loria ",
            "optionC": "  Kesaria ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSanchi Stupa, also written Sanci, is a Buddhist complex, famous for its Great Stupa, on a hilltop at Sanchi Town in Raisen District of the State of Madhya Pradesh, India. It is located in 46 kilometres (29 mi) north-east of Bhopal, capital of Madhya Pradesh. The Great Stupa at Sanchi is one of the oldest stone structures in India, and an important monument of Indian Architecture. It was originally commissioned by the emperor Ashoka in the 2nd century BCE. Its nucleus was a simple hemispherical brick structure built over the relics of the Buddha. It was crowned by the chhatri, a parasol-like structure symbolising high rank, which was intended to honour and shelter the relics. ",
            "keyString": "44195s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, among the following rulers, organised the Second Buddhist Council?",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Kalasoka ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Ananda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the patronage of Kalasoka, The Second Buddhist council took place approximately in 383 BCE, seventy years after the Buddha's parinirv\u0101\u1e47a.",
            "keyString": "44240s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Svetambara Jains were",
            "optionA": "  clad in white ",
            "optionB": "  clad in black ",
            "optionC": "  clad in red ",
            "optionD": "  saffron clad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSvetambara is made from two Sanskrit words \u2013 Svet meaning white &Ambara meaning clothes. So, Svetambara monks are generally clad in a white attire. They believe white represents simplicity which is a must to attain liberation. ",
            "keyString": "44276s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The great exponent of Mahayana Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Ashvaghosa ",
            "optionB": "  Vasubandhu ",
            "optionC": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionD": "  Nagasena ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjuna wrote as a Buddhist monk and as a proponent of the Mahayana (Sanskrit: \"Greater Vehicle\") school, which emphasized the idea of the bodhisattva, or one who seeks to become a buddha; in several of his works he defended the Mahayana sutras as the authentic word of the Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "164479s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Tamil literature was written by Ilango Adigal, brother of Senguvattan, a Chera King and who was a Jain monk is a highly regarded epic?",
            "optionA": "  Kainnilai ",
            "optionB": "  Elathi ",
            "optionC": "  Silappatikaram ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilappatikaram, Tamil literature was written by Ilango Adigal, brother of Senguvattan, a Chera King and who was a Jain monk is a highly regarded epic. ",
            "keyString": "164516s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Indian Religion, there are 24 tirthankaras?",
            "optionA": "  Jainism ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionC": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Sikhism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jainism, a tirthankara (Sanskrit: t\u012brtha\u1e45kara; English: literally a 'ford-maker') is a saviour and spiritual teacher of the dharma (righteous path). The word tirthankara signifies the founder of a tirtha, which is a fordable passage across the sea of interminable births and deaths, the sa\u1e43sara. ",
            "keyString": "164535s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had converted Kanishka to Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Parsva ",
            "optionB": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionC": "  Asvaghosha ",
            "optionD": "  Vasumitra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka in his later days being regretful of his past deeds, had embraced Buddhism for peace and consolation. Asvaghosha virtually converted Kanishka into a Buddhist. ",
            "keyString": "164549s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Jainism the aim of life is to attain Nirvana or Moksha for which one has to",
            "optionA": "  follow three jewels and five vows ",
            "optionB": "  practice, non-violence and non-injury to all living beings ",
            "optionC": "  renounce the world and attain right knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  believe in the Jains and absolute non-violence ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Three Jewels of Jainism. The aim of Jain life is to achieve liberation of the soul. Right faith - Samyak darshana, Right knowledge - Samyak jnana, Right conduct - Samyak charitra. Five Great Vows (Maha-vratas) of Jainism Non-violence - Ahimsa, Truth - Satya, Non-stealing - Achaurya or Asteya, Celibacy/Chastity - Brahmacharya, Non-attachment/Non-possession - Aparigraha. ",
            "keyString": "164562s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is Parinirvana place of Mahavira?",
            "optionA": "  Pava ",
            "optionB": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishali ",
            "optionD": "  Shravanabelagola ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTirthankar Mahavir attained Nirvana at a place called Majjhima Pava, the present Pavapuri in the Patna district of the Indian state of Bihar. ",
            "keyString": "237699s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the patron king of Pataliputra Buddhist Council?",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Kalashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was held in 250 BC at Pataliputra under the patronage of King Asoka. It was presided by Moggliputta Tissa. ",
            "keyString": "237737s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Nalanda was the centre of Buddhist learning in the post-Gupta period.\nReason (R): It was patronised by the Pala rulers.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNalanda was a Mahavihara, a large Buddhist monastery, in the ancient kingdom of Magadha (modern-day Bihar) in India. The site is located about 95 kilometres (59 mi) southeast of Patna near the city of Bihar Sharif, and was a centre of learning from the fifth century CE to c.\u20091200 CE. It is a UNESCO World Heritage Site.Nalanda flourished under the patronage of the Gupta Empire in the 5th and 6th centuries and later under Harsha, the emperor of Kannauj. The liberal cultural traditions inherited from the Gupta age resulted in a period of growth and prosperity until the ninth century. The subsequent centuries were a time of gradual decline, a period during which the tantric developments of Buddhism became most pronounced in eastern India under the Pala Empire. ",
            "keyString": "237755s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is said to be responsible for the spread of Jainism in Karnataka?",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionD": "  Mahapadma Nanda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe spread of Jainism in Karnataka is attributed to Chandragupta Maurya. The Emperor became a Jaina, gave up his throne and spent the last years of his life in Karnataka as a Jaina ascetic. ",
            "keyString": "237772s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the last ruler of India that adopted Jainism in his last days?",
            "optionA": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "optionB": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Gupta Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t According to Jain history, late in his life, Chandragupta adopted Jainism, renounced the empire he built and handed over his power to his son, became a Jaina monk, and headed to meditate and pursue spirituality in the Deccan region, under the Jaina teacher Bhadrabahu at Shravanabelagola. ",
            "keyString": "237786s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the mother of Mahavira?",
            "optionA": "  Yasoda ",
            "optionB": "  Anojja ",
            "optionC": "  Trishala ",
            "optionD": "  Devanandi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrishala, Trishala Devi, Priyakarini, or Trishala Mata was the mother of Mahavira, the 24th Tirthankara of Jainism, and wife of the Jain monarch, Siddartha of Kundgraam, of present-day Bihar. Mahavira was born in Kundgram near Vaishali (Bihar) at 599 B.C. ",
            "keyString": "300757s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddha gave his first religious message at",
            "optionA": "  Rajagriha ",
            "optionB": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Gaya ",
            "optionD": "  Sarnath ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sermon, Buddha gave to the five monks, was his first sermon, called the Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta. It was given on the full-moon day of Asalha Puja. ",
            "keyString": "300796s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddha delivered his first sermon at __________",
            "optionA": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionB": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionC": "  Kapilvastu ",
            "optionD": "  Vaisali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sermon, Buddha gave to the five monks, was his first sermon, called the Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta. It was given on the full-moon day of Asalha Puja. ",
            "keyString": "300814s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following Mudra did Gautam Buddha delivered his first sermon at Saranath?",
            "optionA": "  Abhaya Mudra ",
            "optionB": "  Dhyana Mudra ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmchakra Mudra ",
            "optionD": "  Bhumisparasa Mudra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDharmachakra mudra, used by Buddha during his first sermon following his enlightenment, represents continuous flow of energy.",
            "keyString": "300830s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Third Buddhist Council was patronised by",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Mahakashyap Upali ",
            "optionD": "  Sabakarni ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Third Buddhist council was convened in about 250 BCE at Asokarama in Pataliputra, supposedly under the patronage of Emperor Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "300843s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddhist sect Mahayana formally came into existence during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmapala ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahayana sect of Buddhism emerged during the reign of Kanishka. Asanga was the founder of Mahayan sect of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "353292s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The paintings of Ajanta depict the stories of",
            "optionA": "  Ramayana ",
            "optionB": "  Mahabharta ",
            "optionC": "  Jataka ",
            "optionD": "  Panchatantra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jataka tales are a voluminous body of literature native to India concerning the previous births of Gautama Buddha in both human and animal form. ",
            "keyString": "353330s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the number of monks in the religious family of Ajitnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  50 thousand ",
            "optionB": "  One lakh ",
            "optionC": "  One lakh fifty thousand ",
            "optionD": "  Two lakh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1 lakh monks were there in the religious family of Ajitnath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "353348s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many gandhara were in the religious family of Ajitnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  80 ",
            "optionB": "  85 ",
            "optionC": "  90 ",
            "optionD": "  95 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhara was an ancient kingdom of the Peshawar Valley, extending between the Swat valley and Potohar plateau regions of Pakistan as well as the Jalalabad district of northeastern Afghanistan. There were 95 ganadhara in the religious family of Ajitnath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "353362s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the father of Ajitnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Jitshatru ",
            "optionB": "  Mallinath ",
            "optionC": "  Parsavnath ",
            "optionD": "  Neminath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShree Ajitnath Bhagwan. Ajitnatha was born at Ayodhya in the ikshvaku clan. His father was king Jitashatru raja and mother was queen Vijaya. ",
            "keyString": "353375s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why Rishabnath also called Aadibrahma?",
            "optionA": "  Due to height ",
            "optionB": "  First to tell Moksha Marg ",
            "optionC": "  Religious Conversion ",
            "optionD": "  Showing the path of livelihood ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Rishabhdev also known as Lord Adinath was the first Jain Tirthankar of present time cycle. He lived before civilization developed. Because of this, he had the name of \u0100din\u0101th - the original lord. He became a Siddha, a liberated soul which has destroyed all of its karma. ",
            "keyString": "402643s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After how many years of practice Sambhavnath acquired Kewalya Gyan and formed DharamTirth?",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  12 ",
            "optionC": "  14 ",
            "optionD": "  16 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter 14 years of practice Sambhavnath acquired Kewalya Gyan and formed DharamTirth. ",
            "keyString": "402681s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where Ajitnatha Tirthankar was born?",
            "optionA": "  Ayodhya ",
            "optionB": "  Kiskindha ",
            "optionC": "  Nasik ",
            "optionD": "  Ujjain ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjitnatha was the second tirthankara of the present age, avasarpini (half time cycle) according to Jainism. He was born to King Jitashatru and Queen Vijaya at Ayodhya in the Ikshvaku dynasty. According to Jain beliefs, he became a siddha, a liberated soul which has destroyed all of its karma. ",
            "keyString": "402698s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following systems of Indian Philosophy uphold the ideology of Charvakism, Ajivika, Jainism and Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Orthodox System of Indian Philosophy ",
            "optionB": "  Unorthodox System of Indian Philosophy ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnorthodox systems of Indian Philosophy uphold the ideology of Charvakism, Ajivika, Jainism and Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "402712s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two great Buddhist universities of Nalanda and Vikramshila were patronised by the",
            "optionA": "  Palas ",
            "optionB": "  Paramaras ",
            "optionC": "  Chandelas ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNalanda was a Mahavihara, a large Buddhist monastery, in the ancient kingdom of Magadha. They reportedly chided King Harsha for patronising Nalanda during the great age of the Guptas, was prized and cherished by the Palas. Vikramashila was one of the two most important centres of learning in India during the Pala Empire, along with Nalanda. Vikramashila was one of the largest Buddhist universities,",
            "keyString": "402726s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest Buddhist commentator of the Buddhist canonical literature has been",
            "optionA": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionB": "  Ashvaghosha ",
            "optionC": "  Vasumitra ",
            "optionD": "  Buddhaghosha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAsvagho\u1e63a or Ashvaghosha was a Buddhist philosopher, dramatist, poet and orator from India. He was born in Saketa in northern India. He is believed to have been the first Sanskrit dramatist, and is considered the greatest Indian poet prior to Kalidasa. ",
            "keyString": "450432s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the animals carved on the Sarnath Pillar?",
            "optionA": "  Humped Bull ",
            "optionB": "  Deer ",
            "optionC": "  Elephant ",
            "optionD": "  Horse ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the wall of the cylinder the bull, the horse, the Lion and the Elephant all in the moving position are being placed in between the Chakras. These could symbolize Bull, Lion, Horse and Elephant rolling the Chakras. Pillar was built by Ashoka to mark the site of Buddha's first sermon. ",
            "keyString": "451031s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first image of the Buddha was carved out during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Pusyamitra Shunga ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka I ",
            "optionD": "  Menander ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first image of the Buddha was carved out during the reign of Kanishka I. ",
            "keyString": "451588s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddhism made an important impact by allowing two sections of society into its fold. They were",
            "optionA": "  Merchants and Priests ",
            "optionB": "  Moneylenders and Slaves ",
            "optionC": "  Warriors and Traders ",
            "optionD": "  Women and Sudras ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShudra is the fourth varna, or one of the four social categories found in the texts of Hinduism. Buddha considered the caste system unjust. He asserted that morality and deed should be determined the cast of a person instead of birth. ",
            "keyString": "452173s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Sumtinath Tirthankar receive Shiksha (enlightenment)?",
            "optionA": "  Ayodhya ",
            "optionB": "  Nasik ",
            "optionC": "  Ujjain ",
            "optionD": "  Kiskindha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAyodhya is a city located in Ayodhya district of Uttar Pradesh, India. Sumtinath Tirthankar receive Shiksha (enlightenment) at Ayodhya. ",
            "keyString": "452720s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddha has been eulogized as an ocean of wisdom and compassion in",
            "optionA": "  Buddha-Charita ",
            "optionB": "  Jataka tales ",
            "optionC": "  Amarakosa ",
            "optionD": "  The Light of Aisa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Amarakosha is the popular name for Namalinganushasanam, a thesaurus in Sanskrit written by the ancient Indian scholar Amarasimha. It is the oldest extant kosha. The Buddha has been eulogized as an ocean of wisdom and compassion in Amarakosha. ",
            "keyString": "497006s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A collective term used by the Jains for their sacred books is",
            "optionA": "  Prabandhas ",
            "optionB": "  Angas ",
            "optionC": "  Nibandhas ",
            "optionD": "  Chartis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe knowledge of Shruta-Jnana, may be of things which are contained in the Angas (Limbs or sacred Jain books) or of things outside the Angas. ",
            "keyString": "497042s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Abhinandannath Tirthankar initiated first Parna after how many days of receipt of Diksha?",
            "optionA": "  One ",
            "optionB": "  Two ",
            "optionC": "  Three ",
            "optionD": "  Four ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhagvan Abhinandan was born in Ayodhya, on second day of the bright half of the month of Magh, around midnight. His father name was Samvar and Mother name was Siddharth . After long span of life time, he took diksha on 12th day of the bright half of the month of Magh along with 1000 other ascetics' mens. ",
            "keyString": "497059s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Jain literature, which of the following Tirthankar is also known as Prajapati, Adibrahma and Aadinath?",
            "optionA": "  Rishabhnath ",
            "optionB": "  Ajitnath ",
            "optionC": "  Sambhav nath ",
            "optionD": "  Abhnindan Nath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRishabhanatha is the first Tirthankara (ford maker) in Jainism. A mythical leader, he is believed in Jainism to have lived millions of years ago. He was the first of twenty-four teachers in the present half-cycle of time in Jain cosmology, and called a \"ford maker\" because his teachings helped one across the sea of interminable rebirths and deaths (sa\u1e43sara). He is also known as Adinatha of Jainism which translates into \"First (Adi) Lord (natha)\", as well as Adishvara (first ishvara), Yugadideva (deva of yuga), Prathamaraja (first king), and Nebheya (son of Nabhi). Along with Mahavira, Parshvanatha and Neminatha, Rishabhanatha is one of the four Tirthankaras that attract the most devotional worship among the Jains. ",
            "keyString": "497072s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which Ganarajya Gautam Buddha belonged?",
            "optionA": "  Shibi ",
            "optionB": "  Shakya ",
            "optionC": "  Saurasena ",
            "optionD": "  Shabara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGautama was born as a Kshatriya, the son of Suddhodana, \"an elected chief of the Shakya clan\", whose capital was Kapilavastu, and who were later annexed by the growing Kingdom of Kosala during the Buddha's lifetime. ",
            "keyString": "497084s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the clan Buddha belonged to",
            "optionA": "  Gnathrika ",
            "optionB": "  Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Shakya ",
            "optionD": "  Kuru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Buddha was born into a noble family of the kshatriya varna in Lumbini, Nepal in 563 BCE. He was called Siddhartha Gautama in his childhood. His father was king Suddhodana, leader of the Shakya clan in what was the growing state of Kosala, and his mother was queen Maya Devi. ",
            "keyString": "548505s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Prince of Piligrims' was the name attributed to",
            "optionA": "  Fa-Hien ",
            "optionB": "  Hiuen-tsang ",
            "optionC": "  I-tsing ",
            "optionD": "  Megasthenes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chinese traveller Hiuen Tsang, called the prince of pilgrims visited India during the reign of Harshavardhana. ",
            "keyString": "548635s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The deep transforming effect that the Kalinga War had on Ashoka has been described in",
            "optionA": "  Archaeological excavations ",
            "optionB": "  Rock edicts ",
            "optionC": "  Coins ",
            "optionD": "  Pillar edicts ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe deep transforming effect that the Kalinga War had on Ashoka has been described in rock edicts. ",
            "keyString": "548749s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, according to the Buddhist, is believed to be the next incarnation of Gautam Buddha?",
            "optionA": "  Atreya ",
            "optionB": "  Maitreya ",
            "optionC": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionD": "  Kalki ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Buddhist tradition, Maitreya is a bodhisattva who will appear on Earth in the future, achieve complete enlightenment, and teach the pure dharma. According to scriptures, Maitreya will be a successor to the present Buddha, Gautama Buddha (also known as Sakyamuni Buddha).",
            "keyString": "548803s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vaishakha Purnima has a great significance because it was on this day",
            "optionA": "  Buddha was born ",
            "optionB": "  Buddha got enlightened ",
            "optionC": "  Buddha died ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddha Purnima is called so in India because this auspicious day falls on the full moon day. On the full moon day of Vaishakha, the lunar month corresponds to the month of April-May. In India, Buddha is considered as the eight incarnation of Lord Vishnu. ",
            "keyString": "548847s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tripitakas' are sacred books of",
            "optionA": "  Hindus ",
            "optionB": "  Jains ",
            "optionC": "  Parsis ",
            "optionD": "  Buddhists ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tripitaka (Pali Canon), Mahayana Sutras and the Tibetan Book of the Dead are three major noncanonical Buddhist texts. The Pali Canon, which means \"the word of Buddha,\" includes some of the Buddha's discourse, but it also incorporates the teachings of his pupils. ",
            "keyString": "633169s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In his inscriptions Ashoka called himself",
            "optionA": "  Devanampriya Priyadarshi King ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka Priyadarshi ",
            "optionC": "  Dhammasoka (Dharmasoka) ",
            "optionD": "  Daivaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka refers to himself as \"Beloved of the Gods\" (Devanampiya). The identification of Devanampiya with Ashoka was confirmed by an inscription discovered in 1915 by C. Beadon, a British gold-mining engineer, at Maski, a village in Raichur district of Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "634504s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the meaning of the symbol Horse of Sambhavnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Speed ",
            "optionB": "  Restrained heart ",
            "optionC": "  Anger ",
            "optionD": "  Charm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe meaning of the symbol Horse of Sambhavnath Tirthankar is Restrained heart. ",
            "keyString": "636986s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which language was mostly used for the propagation of Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Prakrit ",
            "optionC": "  Pali ",
            "optionD": "  Sauraseni ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPali is a Middle Indo-Aryan language (of Prakrit group) of the Indian subcontinent. It is best known as the language of many of the earliest extant Buddhist scriptures. as collected in the Pali Canon or Tip taka, and as the liturgical language of Theravada Buddhism. Pali is a literary language of the Prakrit language family. ",
            "keyString": "637200s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Santhara is a religious ritual of__________ community",
            "optionA": "  Sikhs ",
            "optionB": "  Jews ",
            "optionC": "  Jain ",
            "optionD": "  Buddhists ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSallekhana also known as Samlehna, Santhara, Samadhi-marana or Sanyasana-marana; is a supplementary vow to the ethical code of conduct of Jainism. It is the religious practice of voluntarily fasting to death by gradually reducing the intake of food and liquids. It is viewed in Jainism as the thinning of human passions and the body, and another means of destroying rebirth-influencing karma by withdrawing all physical and mental activities. Santhara is a religious ritual of Swetambara Jain. ",
            "keyString": "637299s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddhist Doctrines were written in",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali ",
            "optionC": "  Tibetan ",
            "optionD": "  Not written in any language but orally transmitted ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPali forms are given in the sections on the core teachings of early Buddhism that are reconstructed primarily from Pali texts and in sections that deal with Buddhist traditions in which the primary sacred language is Pali. ",
            "keyString": "715862s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka's claim to be one of the greatest rulers in world history life in the fact that",
            "optionA": "  his aims covered both the religious and secular aspects of life ",
            "optionB": "  he worked for the material moral and spiritual uplift of the people ",
            "optionC": "  after a single conquest he dedicated himself completely to the cause of peace ",
            "optionD": "  he attempted to unify the people of different castes and communities into a bound of common moral ideal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lethal war with Kalinga transformed the revengeful Emperor Ashoka to a stable and peaceful emperor and he became a patron of Buddhism. Nevertheless, his patronage led to the expansion of Buddhism in the Mauryan empire and other kingdoms during his rule, and worldwide from about 250 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "716478s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which language were the Buddhist-texts 'Pitakas' composed?",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Ardhamagadhi ",
            "optionC": "  Pali ",
            "optionD": "  Prakrit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sacred book of Buddhism is called the Tripitaka (called Tipitaka in Pali). It is also called the Pali Canon, after the language in which it was first written. The ancient Indian language, Pali, is very close to the language that the Buddha himself spoke. ",
            "keyString": "717071s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Sumtinath Tirthankar attained Nirvana?",
            "optionA": "  Sammed Shikhar ",
            "optionB": "  Parsnath ",
            "optionC": "  Girnar ",
            "optionD": "  Pawapur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Sumatinath travelled to Sammed Shikarji were after one month of fasting and meditation, he attained nirvana. Moksha-kalyanak: 'Chaitra Shukla Ekadashi' under the constellation Regulus. ",
            "keyString": "717643s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In what respect did Jainism differ from Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  In its stress on the doctrine of ahimsa ",
            "optionB": "  In denying the authority of the Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  In opposing animal sacrifice ",
            "optionD": "  In its attitude towards trade ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJainism differ from Buddhism Ahimsa in its stress on the doctrine of ahimsa. Ahimsa, (Sanskrit: \"noninjury\") in the Indian religions of Jainism, Hinduism, and Buddhism, the ethical principle of not causing harm to other living things. In Jainism, ahimsa is the standard by which all actions are judged. ",
            "keyString": "718168s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is 'Milind panho'?",
            "optionA": "  A Buddhist place ",
            "optionB": "  One of the names of Buddha ",
            "optionC": "  A Buddhist Specimen of Art ",
            "optionD": "  Buddhist text ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Milinda Pa\u00f1ha is a Buddhist text which dates from sometime between 100 BCE and 200 CE. It purports to record a dialogue between the Buddhist sage N\u0101gasena, and the Indo-Greek king Menander I of Bactria, who reigned from Sagala. ",
            "keyString": "787693s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of Masi?",
            "optionA": "  Teaching ",
            "optionB": "  Defence ",
            "optionC": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionD": "  Business ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeaching",
            "keyString": "788269s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Desire is the cause of all sufferings\". Which religion promoted this?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Sikhism ",
            "optionD": "  Hinduism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Buddhism, the belief that desire is the cause of all sufferings is the way to liberate from all sufferings is by eliminating desires. Because desire can cause humans to become obsessed and embittered, it has been called one of the causes of woe for mankind. ",
            "keyString": "788865s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was King Vipulvahan?",
            "optionA": "  Father of Sambhavnath ",
            "optionB": "  Brother of Sambhavnath ",
            "optionC": "  Friend of Sambhavnath ",
            "optionD": "  Teacher of Sambhavnath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKing Vipulvahan came to this world as the third Tirthankara Sambhavnath in his next birth. Such realized souls always carry good deed in all their births. Shravasti King Jitari and Queen Senadevi gave birth to Sambhavnath. ",
            "keyString": "789595s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was Mahavira?",
            "optionA": "  21st Tirthankara ",
            "optionB": "  24th Tirthankara ",
            "optionC": "  23rd Tirthankara ",
            "optionD": "  22nd Tirthankara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahavira, also known as Vardham\u0101na, was the twenty-fourth tirthankara who revived Jainism. In the Jain tradition, it is believed that Mahavira was born in the early part of the 6th century BC into a royal kshatriya family in present-day Bihar, India. ",
            "keyString": "790699s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oldest Jain scriptures are regarded to be the",
            "optionA": "  Fourteen Purvas ",
            "optionB": "  Twelve Upangas ",
            "optionC": "  Twelve Angas ",
            "optionD": "  Fourteen Uparvas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey orally complied the direct preaching of Lord Mahavir into twelve main texts (sutras). These texts are known as Ang-agams. Hence the Ang-agams are the oldest religious scriptures and the back bone of Jain literature. ",
            "keyString": "863824s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the five vows (Panch Anuvratas) of Jainism, four existed before Mahavira. The one which he added was",
            "optionA": "  not to kill (non-injury) ",
            "optionB": "  not to steal ",
            "optionC": "  non-attachment to worldly things ",
            "optionD": "  celibacy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTotal abstinence from sensual pleasure and the pleasure of all five senses are called celibacy. Sensual pleasure is an infatuating force, which sets aside all virtues and reason at the time of indulgence. This vow of controlling sensuality is very difficult to observe in its subtle form. One may refrain from physical indulgence but may still think of the pleasures of sensualism, which is prohibited in Jainism. Monks are required to observe this vow strictly and completely. They should not enjoy sensual pleasures and pleasure of all five senses, ask others to do the same, nor approve of it. There are several rules laid down for observing this vow for householders. They should not any physical relationship other than own spouse. The relationship with your own spouse should be of limited nature. ",
            "keyString": "865525s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What name was given to Rishabhnath Tirthankar due to his father Nabhiraya?",
            "optionA": "  Dharam Nath ",
            "optionB": "  Anantnath ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Prabhu ",
            "optionD": "  Nabhisunu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNabhisunu was the name given to Rishabhnath Tirthankar due to his father Nabhiraya. ",
            "keyString": "867160s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following presided over the Buddhist council held during the reign of Kanishka at Kashmir?",
            "optionA": "  Parsva ",
            "optionB": "  Vasumitra ",
            "optionC": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionD": "  Sudraka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe fourth Buddhist council was held in 72 AD at Kundalvana, Kashmir. It was presided by Vasumitra, while Asvaghosa was his deputy. The council was held under the patronage of Kushan King Kanishka of Kushan Empire. Buddhism was divided into two sects namely Mahayana and Hinayana. ",
            "keyString": "867418s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka's prime claim to greatness lay in",
            "optionA": "  His extensive conquests ",
            "optionB": "  The promotion of people's welfare by him ",
            "optionC": "  His marathon army ",
            "optionD": "  His exclusive patronage of Buddhism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe prime objective of Asoka was to achieve both material and spiritual welfare of men. As for the people\u2019s spiritual welfare he did enormous works for their mental elevation to lead a nobler life according to the laws of Dharma. He made it a principle of administration that a set of special officers \"shall make themselves acquainted with what gives happiness or pain and exhort the people of the provinces along with the faithful, so that they may gain happiness in this world and in the next\". ",
            "keyString": "867631s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the single most important source of the history of Ashoka?",
            "optionA": "  Sri Lankan chronicles Dipavamsa and Mahavamsa ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhist works Divyavadana and Ashokavadana ",
            "optionC": "  Inscriptions of Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Archaeological Sources and the Puranas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka was the third ruler of the Maurya dynasty and was one of the most powerful kings in ancient times. His reign between 273 BC and 232 B.C. in the history of India was one of the most prosperous periods. The Edicts of Ashoka are a collection of more than thirty inscriptions on the pillars as well as boulders and cave walls, made by Emperor Ashoka of the Mauryan Empire during his reign, from 268 BCE to 232 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "934324s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gautama Buddha was brought up by",
            "optionA": "  Mahaprajapati ",
            "optionB": "  Mayadevi ",
            "optionC": "  Kundavi ",
            "optionD": "  Sangamitra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahapajapati Gotami was the step-mother and maternal aunt (mother's sister) of the Buddha. In Buddhist tradition, she was the first woman to seek ordination for women, which she did from Gautama Buddha directly, and she became the first bhikkhuni (Buddhist nun). ",
            "keyString": "935016s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ruler was a contemporary of Buddha?",
            "optionA": "  Udayin ",
            "optionB": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionC": "  Ajatshatru ",
            "optionD": "  Mahapadma Nanda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjatashatru was a king of the Haryanka dynasty of Magadha in East India. He was the son of King Bimbisara and was a contemporary of both Mahavira and Gautama Buddha. Bimbisara the founder of Haryanka dynasty of Magadha empire was the contemporary of lord Buddha.",
            "keyString": "935076s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following rulers was first to embrace Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Ajatasatru ",
            "optionC": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionD": "  Bimbisara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is not just that Ashoka ably ruled this huge empire but the quality of social justice that he brought to his already strong administration. Remorseful after his bloody campaign and conquest of Kalinga, Ashoka embraced Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "935809s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): In the beginning, only high caste Kshatriya communities adopted Jainism. \nReason (R): Vardhaman Mahavira belonged to a well-known Kshatriya community",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahavira, also known as Vardham\u0101na, was the twenty-fourth tirthankara (ford-maker) who revived Jainism. In the Jain tradition, it is believed that Mahavira was born in the early part of the 6th century BC into a royal kshatriya family in present-day Bihar, India. He abandoned all worldly possessions at the age of 30 and left home in pursuit of spiritual awakening, becoming an ascetic. Mahavira practiced intense meditation and severe austerities for 12 years, after which he is believed to have attained Kevala Jnana (omniscience). ",
            "keyString": "935871s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who propounded the 'Eight-Fold Path' for the end of misery of mankind?",
            "optionA": "  Mahavir ",
            "optionB": "  Gautam Buddha ",
            "optionC": "  Adi Shankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe idea of the Eightfold Path appears in what is regarded as the first sermon of the founder of Buddhism, Siddhartha Gautama, known as the Buddha, which he delivered after his enlightenment. There he sets forth a middle way, the Eightfold Path, between the extremes of asceticism and sensual indulgence. These Are, 1. Right View 2. Right Resolve 3. Right Speech 4. Right Conduct 5. Right Livelihood 6. Right effort 7. Right Mindfulness 8. Right Samadhi This eight-fold path leads to 'Nirvana'. ",
            "keyString": "991149s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oil paint was first used for Buddhist paintings by Indian and Chinese painters in western __________ sometime between the fifth and tenth centuries",
            "optionA": "  Iraq ",
            "optionB": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionC": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Oil paint was first used for Buddhist paintings by Indian and Chinese painters in western Afghanistan sometime between the fifth and tenth centuries. ",
            "keyString": "991680s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The founder of Jainism was",
            "optionA": "  Rishbha ",
            "optionB": "  Neminath ",
            "optionC": "  Parsvanatha ",
            "optionD": "  Vardhaman Mahavira ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe founder of Jainism was Vardhaman Mahavira. ",
            "keyString": "992398s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the master of Gautama Buddha?",
            "optionA": "  Alara Kalama ",
            "optionB": "  Kalidas ",
            "optionC": "  Viswamitra ",
            "optionD": "  Vashistha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlara Kalama was a hermit saint and a teacher of ancient meditation. He was the specialist of Samkhya philosophy. According to the Pali Canon scriptures, he was the first teacher of Gautama Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "992450s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka's conquest of Kalinga has been described in the minor rock edict number.",
            "optionA": "  I ",
            "optionB": "  IV ",
            "optionC": "  VIII ",
            "optionD": "  XIII ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka's conquest of Kalinga has been described in the minor rock edict numbered XIII. ",
            "keyString": "992799s13m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Jain centre in South India is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Rameshvaram ",
            "optionB": "  Madurai ",
            "optionC": "  Kanchi ",
            "optionD": "  Shravanbelgola ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famous Jain centre in South India is located at Madurai, Sravanabelgola. It houses 57ft high 'Gommateshwara statue' of Jain God 'Bahubali'. ",
            "keyString": "71780s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The two colossal images of the Buddha at Bamiyan are an instance of the __________ art?",
            "optionA": "  Early Mathura ",
            "optionB": "  Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Gupta ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhara ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Buddhas of Bamiyan were 6th-century monumental statues of Gautam Buddha. It is a site of several Buddhist monasteries, and a thriving center for religion, philosophy, and art. It is an art of Gupta period. ",
            "keyString": "71844s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which of the following is the classic \"Jivaka Chintamani\" in Tamil associated?",
            "optionA": "  Jainism ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionC": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Christianity ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe epic tamil poem, Jivaka Cintamani (also known as Civaka Cintamani) is a Jain religious epic authored by jain saint Tiruttakrdeva. This epic is considered one of the classic epics of Sangam Literature. ",
            "keyString": "72541s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Assamese literature is Buddhist songs composed in the 8th to 12th centuries?",
            "optionA": "  Charyapadas ",
            "optionB": "  Kotha Ramayana ",
            "optionC": "  Drona Parva ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Charyapadas, the Buddhist ballads of 8th-10th century some of whose composers were from Kamarupa and the language of which bear strong affitinities with Assamese (besides Bengali, Maithili and Oriya), are considered the first examples of Assamese literature. The spirit of the Charyapadas are found in later-day Deh-Bicaror Geet and other aphorisms; and some of the ragas found their way to the 15th-16th century Borgeets. ",
            "keyString": "72586s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Manusmriti\nI. Smritis dealt with the performance of duties, customs and laws prescribed according to Dharma.\nII. Consists mainly of dialogues between the Buddha and his followers.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Manusm\u1e5bti also spelled as Manusmriti, is an ancient legal text among the many Dharmasastras of Hinduism. It was one of the first Sanskrit texts to have been translated into English in 1776, by Sir William Jones, and was used to formulate the Hindu law by the British colonial government. ",
            "keyString": "73148s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddhism in Nepal was introduced during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Harshavardhana ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPre-Lichchavi Buddhism. Emperor Ashoka of the Maurya Empire put up a pillar at Lumbini, the birthplace of the Buddha, in the second century BCE. After the Third Buddhist council, Ashoka sent missionaries to Nepal. It is also believed that Ashoka went to Patan and had four stupas built there. ",
            "keyString": "128792s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are beliefs of Buddhism?\nI. The world is full of sorrows.\nII. People suffer on account of desires.\nIII. If desires are conquered, nirvana will be attained.\nIV. The existence of God and Soul must be recognised.",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "optionB": "  II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionD": "  II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddhist philosophy refers to the philosophical investigations and systems of inquiry that developed among various Buddhist schools in India following the death of the Buddha and later spread throughout Asia. The Buddhist path combines both philosophical reasoning and meditation. The four Noble Truths of Buddhism are the world is full of sorrows, Desire is root cause of sorrow, If desire is conquered all sorrows can be removed, Desire can be removed by following the eight-fold path. ",
            "keyString": "129167s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the number of Gandhars of Abhinandannath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  112 ",
            "optionB": "  114 ",
            "optionC": "  116 ",
            "optionD": "  118 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere have been an infinite number of tirthankaras in the past time periods. There were 116 Gandhars of Abhinandannath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "129216s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of first Gandhar of Abhinandannath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Vajrnath ",
            "optionB": "  Vipul ",
            "optionC": "  Chandra Prabhu ",
            "optionD": "  Vasu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of first Gandhar of Abhinandannath Tirthankar was Vajrnath. ",
            "keyString": "129565s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the mother of Abhinandananatha Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Vijaya ",
            "optionB": "  Tara ",
            "optionC": "  Siddharta Devi ",
            "optionD": "  Marudevi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhinandananatha or Abhinandana Swami was the fourth Tirthankara of the present age (Avasarpini). He is said to have lived for 50 lakh purva. He was born to King Sanvara and Queen Siddhartha at Ayodhya in the Ikshvaku clan. ",
            "keyString": "129912s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka called the Third Buddhist Council at",
            "optionA": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionB": "  Magadha ",
            "optionC": "  Kalinga ",
            "optionD": "  Sarnath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Third Buddhist council was convened in about 250 BCE at Asokarama in Pataliputra, supposedly under the patronage of Emperor Ashoka. This is however disputed, as mention of the council never appears in the Edicts of Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "195640s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Hindi month Sumtinath Tirthankar received diksha?",
            "optionA": "  Vaisakh ",
            "optionB": "  Jyestha ",
            "optionC": "  Chetra ",
            "optionD": "  Magha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn Vaishaka Shukla 9, in Ayodhya, in a jungle, he removed his hair in just five hand full, removed all the worldly things from his body and became and ascetic and disappeared in jungle. ",
            "keyString": "195853s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Jainism, 'Perfect Knowledge' is referred to as",
            "optionA": "  Nirvana ",
            "optionB": "  Ratna ",
            "optionC": "  Kaivalya ",
            "optionD": "  Jina ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaivalya also known as Kevala Jnana means omniscience in Jainism and is roughly translated as absolute knowledge or supreme knowledge. Kevala jnana is believed to be an intrinsic quality of all souls. This quality is masked by karmic particles that surround the soul. Every soul has the potential to obtain omniscience by shedding off these karmic particles. Jain scriptures speak of twelve stages through which the soul achieves this goal. A soul who has attained kevala jnana is called a kevalin. According to the Jains, only kevalins can comprehend objects in all aspects and manifestations; others are only capable of partial knowledge. ",
            "keyString": "197420s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the ceremony of initiation of education in Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Siksha ",
            "optionB": "  Upanayanam ",
            "optionC": "  Pabajja ",
            "optionD": "  Diksha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPabbajja literally means \"to go forth\" and refers to when a layperson leaves home to live the life of a Buddhist renunciate among a community of bhikkhus. This generally involves preliminary ordination as a novice. It is sometimes referred to as \"lower ordination.\" ",
            "keyString": "201371s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The language which contributed to the spread of Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil ",
            "optionD": "  Greek ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddha preached his teachings in Pali(the language of the common people) which accounted for the spread of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "201965s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jainism was divided into two sects - Swetambaras (White-clad) and Digambaras (Sky clad or naked) - During the reign of the",
            "optionA": "  Nandas ",
            "optionB": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionC": "  Kusanas ",
            "optionD": "  Shungas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The two sects formed in the 4th century BCE following a migration of Jain monks southward from the Ganges River (or from Ujjain) to Karnataka in response to a serious famine during the reign of Chandragupta Maurya. ",
            "keyString": "251791s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Indo-Greek king to embrace Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Alexander ",
            "optionB": "  Strato I ",
            "optionC": "  Menander ",
            "optionD": "  Democritus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMenander I Soter was an Indo-Greek King of the Indo-Greek Kingdom (165[3]/155[3] \u2013130 BC) who administered a large empire in the Northwestern regions of the Indian Subcontinent from his capital at Sagala. Menander is noted for having become a patron of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "251830s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is known as the Jain Temple City?",
            "optionA": "  Girnar ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Rajagriha ",
            "optionD": "  Varanasi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGirnar Jain temples -The group temples of Jainism are situated on the Girnar mountains in the Junagadh District of Gujarat, India, situated near Junagadh. There are temples on the hill sacred to the Digambara and the Svetambara branches of Jainism. ",
            "keyString": "251850s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahavira was born in a Kshatriya clan by the name of",
            "optionA": "  Shakya ",
            "optionB": "  Janatrika ",
            "optionC": "  Mallas ",
            "optionD": "  Lichhavis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJantrika Vardhamana Mahavir belonged an aristocratic family and Kshatriya clan called Naya or Jnatri. He was born in Kundagrama, near modern Patna and his father was King of this area. His mother, Trishala was sister of Chetak (Cetakka) an eminent Lichchvi prince of Vaisali. ",
            "keyString": "251864s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following signs was etched on the right leg of Rishabhnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Cow ",
            "optionB": "  Bull ",
            "optionC": "  Elephant ",
            "optionD": "  Tiger ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBull signs was etched on the right leg of Rishabhanatha Tirthankara. ",
            "keyString": "251879s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the doctrines of Jainism was added by Mahavira?",
            "optionA": "  Do not speak a lie ",
            "optionB": "  Observe continence ",
            "optionC": "  Do not commit violence ",
            "optionD": "  Do not steal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahavira added the principle of chastity to the four Jain principles already given by Parshva (no violence, no lying, no stealing, no possessions). According to tradition Mahavira is said to have established a community of 14,000 monks and 36,000 nuns before he died. ",
            "keyString": "297132s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sumtinath Tirthankara was born from whose womb?",
            "optionA": "  Tara ",
            "optionB": "  Marudevi ",
            "optionC": "  Vijaya ",
            "optionD": "  Sumangla ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Sumatinatha was the fifth Jain Tirthankara of the present age (Avasarpini). Sumatinatha was born to Kshatriya King Megha (Meghaprabha) and Queen Mangala (Sumangala) at Ayodhya in the Ikshvaku dynasty. His Janma Kalyanak (birthday) was the eighth day of the Vaisakha Sudi month of the Jain calendar. ",
            "keyString": "297196s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Because of his virtuous deeds Ajitnath Tirthankara was born from whose womb?",
            "optionA": "  Vijaya ",
            "optionB": "  Tara ",
            "optionC": "  Sharmestha ",
            "optionD": "  Geeta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQueen Vijaya Devi saw fourteen auspicious dreams. Vaijayanti, the wife of king Jitshatru's younger brother, Sumitra, also saw the same fourteen dreams. This was a queer coincidence. When the augurs were consulted they advised that Vijaya Devi would give birth to a Tirthankar and Vaijayanti to a Chakravarti (Emperor). During the queen's pregnancy, the influence of king Jitshatru was enhanced to such an extant that even the enemy kingdoms sought and negotiated friendly treaties with him. It became a common practice to say, \"King Jitshatru is invincible (Ajit).\" ",
            "keyString": "297245s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a category into which Ashoka's monuments may be grouped?",
            "optionA": "  Stupas ",
            "optionB": "  Pillars ",
            "optionC": "  Viharas ",
            "optionD": "  Caves ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tViharas as monasteries. The early history of viharas is unclear. Monasteries in the form of caves are dated to centuries before the start of the common era, for Ajivikas, Buddhists and Jainas. The rock-cut architecture found in cave viharas from the 2nd-century BCE have roots in the Maurya Empire period. ",
            "keyString": "297289s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After receipt of Diksha, under which tree Abhinandannath Tirthankar attained Kaivalya gyan (enlightenment)?",
            "optionA": "  Neem ",
            "optionB": "  Devdar ",
            "optionC": "  Vat ",
            "optionD": "  Priyangu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter receipt of Diksha, under Devdar tree Abhinandannath Tirthankar attained Kaivalya gyan (enlightenment). ",
            "keyString": "297325s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which religion is Kaivalya associated?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Sikhism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaivalya also known as Kevala Jnana means omniscience in Jainism. Kaivalya '(detachment) is the Jain concept of salvation'. It is the liberation from rebirth. ",
            "keyString": "342148s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How was the marital life of Ajitnath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Normal ",
            "optionB": "  Good ",
            "optionC": "  Very Good ",
            "optionD": "  Very bad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjitnath Tirthankar married life was very bad. ",
            "keyString": "342189s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why did King Vipulvahan develop aversion for worldly life?",
            "optionA": "  Because of wife ",
            "optionB": "  Because of son ",
            "optionC": "  Because of famine ",
            "optionD": "  Because of subjects ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKing Vipulvahan developed aversion for worldly life because of feminine. ",
            "keyString": "342207s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Lord Buddha breathe his last?",
            "optionA": "  Rajgir ",
            "optionB": "  Bodh Gaya ",
            "optionC": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionD": "  Kushinagar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKushinagar - A Buddhist Pilgrimage where God of Peace and Non-Violence Buddha gave his last sermon and was cremated.",
            "keyString": "342222s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lord Mahavira died at",
            "optionA": "  Saravana Belagola ",
            "optionB": "  Lumbini Garden ",
            "optionC": "  Kalugumalai ",
            "optionD": "  Pavapuri ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Mahavira died at Pavapuri. Pavapuri or Pawa is a holy site for Jains located in the Nalanda district in the Bihar state of Eastern India. It is located about 19 kilometers from Rajgir,14 km from Bihar Sharif and 101 kilometers from Patna, the capital of Bihar. ",
            "keyString": "342236s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct chronological order of the four Buddhist councils held Is",
            "optionA": "  Rajagriha, Kashmir or Jullandhar, Pataliputra, Vaishali ",
            "optionB": "  Vaishali, Rajagriha, Kashmir or Jullandhar, Pataliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Rajagriha, Vaishali, Pataliputra, Kashmir or Jullandhar ",
            "optionD": "  Pataliputra, Rajagriha, Kashmir or Jullandhar, Vaishali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct chronological order of the four Buddhist councils held Is Rajagriha, Vaishali, Pataliputra, Kashmir or Jullandhar. ",
            "keyString": "420142s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most striking feature of the Ashokan pillars is their",
            "optionA": "  monolithic structure ",
            "optionB": "  carving ",
            "optionC": "  polish ",
            "optionD": "  uniformity of workmanship ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe capital is carved out of a single block of polished sandstone, and was always a separate piece from the column itself. ",
            "keyString": "420176s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gautama Buddha was born at",
            "optionA": "  Kusinagar ",
            "optionB": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionC": "  Bodha Gaya ",
            "optionD": "  Lumbini ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t According to the Buddhist tradition, Gautama was born in Lumbini, now in modern-day Nepal, and raised in the Shakya capital of Kapilvastu, which may have been either in what is present day Tilaurakot, Nepal or Piprahwa, India. ",
            "keyString": "420189s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the ruler whose patronage had been enjoyed by Jainism",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Kharavela ",
            "optionC": "  Pushyamitra Sunga ",
            "optionD": "  Samudragupta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKharavela was a king of Kalinga in present-day Odisha, India. He ruled somewhere around first or second century BCE. His name is also transliterated as Kharabe\u1e37a. He is the best known king of the Mahameghavahana dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "420201s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddha's Eight Fold Path did not include",
            "optionA": "  Right Resolve ",
            "optionB": "  Right Views ",
            "optionC": "  Right Speech ",
            "optionD": "  Right Table Manners ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Eightfold Path consists of eight practices: right view, right resolve, right speech, right conduct, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right samadhi ('meditative absorption or union'). The Noble Eightfold Path is one of the principal teachings of Theravada Buddhism, taught to lead to Arhatship. ",
            "keyString": "420213s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following School of art noted for its vitality and assimilative character just because of Brahmanism, Jainism and Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Gandhara School of Art ",
            "optionB": "  Amaravati School of Art ",
            "optionC": "  Mathura School of art ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMathura School of art noted for its vitality and assimilative character just because of Brahmanism, Jainism and Buddhism. Mathura art refers to a particular school of Buddhist art, which centered on the city of Mathura, in central northern India, during the period in which Buddhism flourished in India. The art of Mathura is usually contrasted with the Greco-Buddhist art of Gandhara. ",
            "keyString": "460750s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the reign of Kanishka, Buddhism for the first time went to China and from China it went to",
            "optionA": "  Burma and Tibet ",
            "optionB": "  Thailand and Cambodia ",
            "optionC": "  Korea and Japan ",
            "optionD": "  Indonesia and Vietnam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Kanishka conquests and patronage of Buddhism played an important role in the development of the Silk Road, and in the transmission of Mahayana Buddhism from Gandhara across the Karakoram range to China and than to Korea and Japan. ",
            "keyString": "460797s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Jainis, at which place Abhinandannath attained Nirvana?",
            "optionA": "  Sammed Shikhar ",
            "optionB": "  Shri Keshriyaji Tirtha ",
            "optionC": "  Parasnath ",
            "optionD": "  Sarnath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Jainis, at Sammed Shikhar Abhinandannath attained Nirvana. Shikharji (Sikharji), Giridih district, Jharkhand, India, is located on Parasnath hill, the highest mountain in the state of Jharkhand. It is the most important Jain Tirtha (pilgrimage site) for the Jains, believed to be the place where twenty of the twenty-four Jain tirthankaras along with many other monks attained Moksha, according to Nirvana Kanda and other texts. ",
            "keyString": "460823s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To whom is the introduction of Buddhism into China traditionally attributed?",
            "optionA": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionB": "  Samprati ",
            "optionC": "  Vasubandhu ",
            "optionD": "  Kashyapa Matanga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKasyapa Matanga or Jia Yemoteng was an Indian Buddhist monk who is traditionally believed to have first introduced Buddhism to China in the 1st century CE. According to popular accounts of Chinese Buddhism, Emperor Ming of Han dreamt of a golden deity interpreted as the Buddha and sent a delegation to India. ",
            "keyString": "460847s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka expresses his faith in the Buddhist creed in the",
            "optionA": "  Rummindei inscription ",
            "optionB": "  Schism edict ",
            "optionC": "  Kandhar inscription ",
            "optionD": "  Bhabru edict ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka expresses his faith in the Buddhist creed in the Bhabru edict. ",
            "keyString": "460868s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Jains, what was the number of Gandhars of Sumtinath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  50 ",
            "optionB": "  100 ",
            "optionC": "  150 ",
            "optionD": "  200 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Jains, there was 100 number of Gandhars of Sumtinath Tirthankar. ",
            "keyString": "502715s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddhism was divided into Mahayana and Hinayana during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Asoka ",
            "optionB": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionC": "  Menander ",
            "optionD": "  Harsha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the death of Buddha, Buddhism was divided into two sects namely Mahayana and Hinayana. The terms Hinayana (Lesser Vehicle or Modest Vehicle) and Mahayana (Greater Vehicle or Vast Vehicle) originated in The Prajnaparamita Sutras (The Sutras on Far-Reaching Discriminating Awareness, The Perfection of Wisdom Sutras). It was divided during the reign of Kanishka. ",
            "keyString": "502754s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct language in which Jain and Buddhist literature were written?",
            "optionA": "  Prakrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPali and Prakrit rose to prominence when these were adopted by Buddhist and Jain Sect in ancient India as their sacred language. ",
            "keyString": "502773s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rulers did not enter the Buddhist Cold?",
            "optionA": "  Harsha ",
            "optionB": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSamudragupta did not enter the Buddhist Cold. ",
            "keyString": "502788s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddha, Dhamma and Sangha together are known as",
            "optionA": "  Triratna ",
            "optionB": "  Trivarga ",
            "optionC": "  Trisarga ",
            "optionD": "  Trimurti ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTriratna, (Sanskrit: \"Three Jewels\") Pali Ti-ratana, also called Threefold Refuge, in Buddhism the Triratna comprises the Buddha, the dharma (doctrine, or teaching), and the sangha (the monastic order, or community). ",
            "keyString": "502803s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the ultimate goal of education in Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  Non-violence ",
            "optionB": "  Renunciation ",
            "optionC": "  Moksha ",
            "optionD": "  Voluntary promotion of human welfare ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jainism, moksha is the highest and the noblest objective that a soul should strive to achieve. In fact, it is the only objective that a person should have; other objectives are contrary to the true nature of soul. With the right view, knowledge and efforts all souls can attain this state. That is why Jainism is also known as mok\u1e63am\u0101rga or the \"path to liberation\". ",
            "keyString": "542590s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The monolithic image of Jain Saint 'Gomatiswara' is at __________",
            "optionA": "  Mount Abu ",
            "optionB": "  Shravanbelagola ",
            "optionC": "  Kusinagara ",
            "optionD": "  Kalinga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGommateshwara Statue is a 57-foot (17 m) high monolithic statue located on Vindyagiri at Shravanbelagola in the Indian state of Karnataka. Vindyagiri Hill is one of the two hills in Shravanabelagola; the other is Chandragiri, which is also a seat of several ancient Jain centers, much older than Gommateshwara statue. ",
            "keyString": "542624s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following rulers had embraced Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionC": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionD": "  Pulakesin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta Maurya embraced Jainism towards the end of his life and stepped down from the throne in favour of his son Bindusara. ",
            "keyString": "542643s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which tree Sumtinath Tirthankar received Kaivalya Gyan?",
            "optionA": "  Devdar ",
            "optionB": "  Neem ",
            "optionC": "  Priyangu ",
            "optionD": "  Vat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Priyangu tree Sumtinath Tirthankar received Kaivalya Gyan. ",
            "keyString": "542656s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The principles of Ashoka's Dharma (Dhamma) were taken from",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmanism ",
            "optionD": "  The moral virtues of all Indian religions of that period ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principles of Ashoka's Dharma (Dhamma) were taken from the moral virtues of all Indian religions of that period. ",
            "keyString": "542668s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mention the place where Buddha attained enlightenment.",
            "optionA": "  Sarnath ",
            "optionB": "  Bodh Gaya ",
            "optionC": "  Kapilavastu ",
            "optionD": "  Rajgriha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBodh Gaya is a religious site and place of pilgrimage associated with the Mahabodhi Temple Complex in Gaya district in the Indian state of Bihar. It is famous as it is the place where Gautama Buddha is said to have obtained Enlightenment (Pali: bodhi) under what became known as the Bodhi Tree. ",
            "keyString": "587329s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Buddha means",
            "optionA": "  The Enlightened one ",
            "optionB": "  The Religious Preacher ",
            "optionC": "  The Genius ",
            "optionD": "  The Powerful ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuddha literally means enlightened one or a person who attained Boddhi which means wisdom (highest intellectual or virtue). It means a person who attained highest level of life status. ",
            "keyString": "587365s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Outside India, Buddhism was first accepted in",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Japan ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionD": "  Tibet ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first evidence of the religion spreading outside India coincides with Ashoka's rule as he sent emissaries to Sri Lanka and an area called Suvarnabhumi. ",
            "keyString": "587383s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is the great Buddhist work consisting of dialogues between the Indo-Greek King Menander and the Buddhist philosopher Nagasena?",
            "optionA": "  Milinda Panha ",
            "optionB": "  Arthsashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Jataka ",
            "optionD": "  Kumarasambhava ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Milindapanha is one of the great classics of Pali Buddhist literature, a spirited dialogue between the Greek king Milinda and the Buddhist sage Nagasena. ",
            "keyString": "587396s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of Kaivalya Gyan (enlightenment) received by Abhinandannath Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Shastra Gyan ",
            "optionB": "  Sangeet Siksha ",
            "optionC": "  Nartya Siksha ",
            "optionD": "  Brahma Vidya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe meaning of Kaivalya Gyan (enlightenment) received by Abhinandannath Tirthankar was brahma Vidya. ",
            "keyString": "587409s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Tirthankara of the Jains was",
            "optionA": "  Arishtanemi ",
            "optionB": "  Parshvanath ",
            "optionC": "  Ajitanath ",
            "optionD": "  Rishabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first tirthankara in this present time cycle was Rishabhanatha, who is credited for formulating and organising humans to live in a society harmoniously.",
            "keyString": "623940s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The language in which Buddha preached?",
            "optionA": "  Hindi ",
            "optionB": "  Urdu ",
            "optionC": "  Pali ",
            "optionD": "  Hebrew ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Pali Canon, Buddha taught in local or folks language. He avoided the scholars' language, i.e. Sanskrit. ",
            "keyString": "623976s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gautam Buddha as a prince was known as",
            "optionA": "  Gautam ",
            "optionB": "  Siddhartha ",
            "optionC": "  Rahul ",
            "optionD": "  Suddhodhana ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Buddha, or \"enlightened one,\" was born Siddhartha (which means \"he who achieves his aim\") Gautama to a large clan called the Shakyas in Lumbini, (today, modern Nepal) in the 6th century B.C. ",
            "keyString": "623992s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka was much influenced by Buddhist monk called",
            "optionA": "  Upagupta ",
            "optionB": "  Vasubandhu ",
            "optionC": "  Ambhi ",
            "optionD": "  Asvagosha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUpagupta was a Buddhist monk. According to some stories in the Sanskrit text Ashokavadana, he was the spiritual teacher of the Mauryan emperor Ashoka.",
            "keyString": "624006s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ruler founded the famous Vikramshila University for the Buddhists?",
            "optionA": "  Mahipala ",
            "optionB": "  Devapala ",
            "optionC": "  Gopala ",
            "optionD": "  Dharampala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVikramashila was founded by P\u0101la king Dharmapala in the late 8th or early 9th century. ",
            "keyString": "624019s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are mantra of Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  All sinful acts are renounced for life-long ",
            "optionB": "  All philanthropies acts are renounced for life-long ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll sinful acts are renounced for life-long is mantra of Jainism. ",
            "keyString": "649836s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the ruler whose reign was a witness to both Vardhaman Mahavira and the Buddha preaching their respective doctrines?",
            "optionA": "  Udayin ",
            "optionB": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionC": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionD": "  Harshvardhana ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBimbisara reign was a witness to both Vardhaman Mahavir and the Buddha preaching their respective doctrine. ",
            "keyString": "687657s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Jaina saint credited with the spread of Jainism in Karnataka (south India) was",
            "optionA": "  Bhadrabahu ",
            "optionB": "  Adinatha ",
            "optionC": "  Parshvanatha ",
            "optionD": "  Mahavira ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Bhadrabahu was the Jaina saint that credited with the spread of Jainism in Karnataka (south India). ",
            "keyString": "687693s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For how many years Ajitnath Tirthankar practise harsh austerity?",
            "optionA": "  Ten ",
            "optionB": "  Twelve ",
            "optionC": "  Fourteen ",
            "optionD": "  Sixteen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe led a pious life in spite of the available princely grandeur. At an appropriate time, he became an ascetic under Arindam Suri. Meditating about the omniscient and liberated souls and indulging in harsh penance for 12 years, he purified his soul to a level where he could earn the Tirthankar-nam-and-gotra-karma. Completing his age, he reincarnated as a god in the Viaya- anuttar-dimension. After completing his age in the dimension of gods, he descended into the womb of queen Vijaya Devi, wife of king Jitshaturu of Ayodhya . ",
            "keyString": "687710s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Before starting of an Era, what was the last karma given by Rishabhanatha other than agriculture, ink, sword, craft and service?",
            "optionA": "  Business ",
            "optionB": "  Fishery ",
            "optionC": "  War ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBefore starting of an Era, Business was the last karma given by Rishabhanatha other than agriculture, ink, sword, craft and service, he taught agriculture hence, the means of agriculture, business and self-protection. ",
            "keyString": "687724s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of the preaching mudra of gesture, in which the Buddha is depicted delivering his first sermon, In the Gandhara Sculptures?",
            "optionA": "  Abhaya ",
            "optionB": "  Dhyana ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmachakra ",
            "optionD": "  Bhumisparsha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDharmachakra mudra is one of such interesting and unique hand gestures used in Buddha statues which means the wheel of Dharma in Buddhism. The Dharmachakra mudra is also known as gesture of Teaching of the Wheel of Dharma. This gesture depicts one of the most important moment in Buddha's life as he performed the Dharmachakra mudra in his first sermon in Sarnath after he attained enlightenment. ",
            "keyString": "687737s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhara school of art came into existence in",
            "optionA": "  Hinayana sect ",
            "optionB": "  Mahayana sect ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishnava sect ",
            "optionD": "  Shaiva sect ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhara school of art came into existence in Mahayana sect. Mahayana sect believes in idols worship of Buddha and Bodhisattvas.",
            "keyString": "730371s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The site of birth (nativity) of Gautam Buddha is marked by",
            "optionA": "  A monastery ",
            "optionB": "  A \"Rummindei Pillar\" of Ashok Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  A statue ",
            "optionD": "  A Peepal Tree ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka (r 272-231 BC) was a Mauryan king who converted to Buddhism in the middle of his reign and spent the rest of his life propagating his dharma (law). In order to spread the word of Buddhism he had numerous edicts inscribed on pillars and placed throughout his empire. ",
            "keyString": "730404s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name assigned to Rishabhnath Tirthankar because of the mark on his right leg?",
            "optionA": "  Hiranyagarbha ",
            "optionB": "  Prajapati ",
            "optionC": "  Rishabh ",
            "optionD": "  Vrihad Deva ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRishabh was the name assigned to Rishabhnath Tirthankar because of the mark on his right leg( bull mark and bull literally means Rishabh). ",
            "keyString": "730418s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the mother of Rishabhnath?",
            "optionA": "  Tara ",
            "optionB": "  Sharemestha ",
            "optionC": "  Marudevi ",
            "optionD": "  Anuradha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Jain traditional accounts, he was born to king Nabhi and queen Marudevi in the north Indian city of Ayodhya, also called Vinita. He had two wives, Sunanda and Sumangala. Sumangala is described as the mother of his ninety-nine sons (including Bharata) and one daughter, Brahmi. ",
            "keyString": "730430s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Buddhist scholar Ashvaghosha was a contemporary of which one of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionC": "  Harsha ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka I or Kanishka the Great, an emperor of the Kushan dynasty in the second century (c. 127\u2013150 CE), is famous for his military, political, and spiritual achievements. Asvaghosa or Ashvaghosh was a Buddhist philosopher, dramatist, poet and orator from India. He was born in Saketa in northern India. He is believed to have been the first Sanskrit dramatist. ",
            "keyString": "730442s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Buddhism 'Bull' is related to what incident of Buddha's life?",
            "optionA": "  Birth ",
            "optionB": "  Mahabhimiskramana ",
            "optionC": "  Enlightenment ",
            "optionD": "  Mahaparinirvana ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Buddhism 'Bull' is related to Janma(Birth) incident of Buddha's life Birth. ",
            "keyString": "805309s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the moral of the horse?",
            "optionA": "  Politeness ",
            "optionB": "  Restraint ",
            "optionC": "  Knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the three moral of the horse i.e, Politeness, Restraint and Knowledge. ",
            "keyString": "805347s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fourth Buddhist Council was held at",
            "optionA": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionB": "  Vaishali ",
            "optionC": "  Kundalavana ",
            "optionD": "  Bodh Gaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFourth Buddhist Council was held in the Sarvastivada tradition, said to have been convened by the Kushan emperor Kanishka, in 78 AD at Kundalban in Kashmir. ",
            "keyString": "805361s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the father of Rishabhanatha Tirthankar?",
            "optionA": "  Nabhiraya ",
            "optionB": "  Sambhavnath ",
            "optionC": "  Sumitnath ",
            "optionD": "  Vasupujya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Jain traditional accounts, he was born to king Nabhi and queen Marudevi in the north Indian city of Ayodhya, also called Vinita. He had two wives, Sunanda and Sumangala. Sumangala is described as the mother of his ninety-nine sons (including Bharata) and one daughter, Brahmi. ",
            "keyString": "805373s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vardhamana Mahavira is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Jina ",
            "optionB": "  Great teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Great preacher ",
            "optionD": "  Jain ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVardhamana Mahavira is also known as 'Jina', the one who conquered temptations for sensual pleasures, and hence the name Jainism for the religion he shaped up and propagated from the teachings of his predecessors. ",
            "keyString": "805384s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tutor of Alexander, the Great was",
            "optionA": "  Darius ",
            "optionB": "  Cyrus ",
            "optionC": "  Socrates ",
            "optionD": "  Aristotle ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring his youth, Alexander was tutored by Aristotle until age 16. After Philip's assassination in 336 BC, he succeeded his father to the throne and inherited a strong kingdom and an experienced army. ",
            "keyString": "895797s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Pitaka that contains pronouncements attributed to the Buddha, laying down numerous rules for the conduct of the order is",
            "optionA": "  Vinaya Pitaka ",
            "optionB": "  Sutta Pitaka ",
            "optionC": "  Abhidhamma Pitaka ",
            "optionD": "  All the three Pitakas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vinaya Pitaka contains pronouncements attributed to Buddha, laying down numerous rules for the conduct of the order. ",
            "keyString": "895836s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddhist monk who spread Buddhism in Tibet was",
            "optionA": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionB": "  Ananda ",
            "optionC": "  Asanga ",
            "optionD": "  Padmasambhava ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPadmasambhava also known as Guru Rimpoche the Indian Buddhist monk spread the Buddhism in Tibet. He even helped in the construction of first Buddhist monastery in Tibet. In Tibetan Buddhism, he is a character of a genre of literature called terma, an emanation of Amit\u0101bha that is said to appear to tert\u00f6ns in visionary encounters and a focus of guru yoga practice, particularly in the Rim\u00e9 schools. ",
            "keyString": "895853s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the \"Tri Ratna\" of Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  Right faith ",
            "optionB": "  Right knowledge ",
            "optionC": "  Right view ",
            "optionD": "  Right conduct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jainism the three jewels (also referred to as ratnatraya) are understood as samyagdarshana (\"right faith\"), samyagjnana (\"right knowledge\"), and samyakcharitra (\"right conduct\"). The Triratna is symbolized frequently in art as a trident. ",
            "keyString": "895867s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The original Buddhist religious texts had been written in",
            "optionA": "  Brahmi ",
            "optionB": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionC": "  Pali ",
            "optionD": "  Magadhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sacred book of Buddhism is called the Tripitaka (called Tipitaka in Pali). It is also called the Pali Canon, after the language in which it was first written. The ancient Indian language, Pali, is very close to the language that the Buddha himself spoke. Buddhism is based on Buddha's teachings. ",
            "keyString": "895879s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first Buddhist Council held?",
            "optionA": "  Vaishali ",
            "optionB": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Rajagriha ",
            "optionD": "  Pataliputra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the scriptures of all Buddhist schools, the first Buddhist Council was held soon after the death of the Buddha, dated by the majority of recent scholars around 400 BCE, under the patronage of the king Ajatashatru with the monk Mahakasyapa presiding, at Sattapanni caves Rajgriha (now Rajgir). ",
            "keyString": "984895s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first nun of Gautama Buddha?",
            "optionA": "  Meenakshi ",
            "optionB": "  Smriti ",
            "optionC": "  Gautami ",
            "optionD": "  Gargi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahapajapati Gotami (Pali; Sanskrit Mahaprajapati Gautam\u012b) was the step-mother and maternal aunt (mother's sister) of the Buddha. In Buddhist tradition, she was the first woman to seek ordination for women, which she did from Gautama Buddha directly, and she became the first bhikkhuni (Buddhist nun). ",
            "keyString": "984930s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not included in the 'Eight Fold Path' of Buddhism?",
            "optionA": "  Right Speech ",
            "optionB": "  Right Effort ",
            "optionC": "  Right Desire ",
            "optionD": "  Right Conduct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Eightfold Path consists of eight practices: right view, right resolve, right speech, right conduct, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right samadhi ('meditative absorption or union'). The Noble Eightfold Path is one of the principal teachings of Theravada Buddhism, taught to lead to Arhatship. ",
            "keyString": "984947s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Jaina literature is known as",
            "optionA": "  Tripitakas ",
            "optionB": "  Epics ",
            "optionC": "  Aryasutras ",
            "optionD": "  Angas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJain Literature - Agam literature consists of many texts, which are the sacred books of the Jain religion. They are written in the Ardha-magadhi Prakrit language. Non-agam literature consists of commentary and explanation of Agam literature, and independent works, compiled by ascetics and scholars. ",
            "keyString": "984960s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The earlier Buddhist sculptures had shied away from depicting the image of the Buddha, except through such symbols as",
            "optionA": "  Footprints ",
            "optionB": "  The Bodhi Tree ",
            "optionC": "  Stupas ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe footprint, which denotes both his former physical presence on earth and his temporal absence. The bodhi tree, which represents the place of his enlightenment (under the tree) and comes to symbolize the enlightenment experience itself. The stupa, the reliquary in which the Buddha's physical remains are contained a powerful symbol of both his physical death and continued presence in the world. ",
            "keyString": "984974s14m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was Ajitnath Tirthankara in his previous life?",
            "optionA": "  Siddharth ",
            "optionB": "  Maharaj Vimalvahan ",
            "optionC": "  Mahavir ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe soul that became Bhagavan Ajitnath, in its earlier incarnation, was the great king Vimalvahan of Susima city in Mahavideh area. He purified his soul to a level where he could earn the Tirthankar-nam-and-gotra-karma. When king Jitshatru became old and wanted to devote the last part his life to spiritual pursuit. ",
            "keyString": "30250s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After receipt of Diksha, with which food Abhinandannath Tirthankar initiated first Parna?",
            "optionA": "  Milk ",
            "optionB": "  Kheer ",
            "optionC": "  Water ",
            "optionD": "  Dahi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter receipt of Diksha,Abhinandannath Tirthankar initiated kheer for first Parna. ",
            "keyString": "30285s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The aim of Ashoka's Dhamma was",
            "optionA": "  Subtle conquest ",
            "optionB": "  Religious domination ",
            "optionC": "  A casteless society ",
            "optionD": "  Non-violence and peace ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe policy of Dhamma also laid stress on non-violence and peace, which was to be practiced by giving up war and conquests and also as a restraint on the killing of animals. However, Ashoka realized that a certain display of his political might may be necessary to keep the primitive forest-dwelling tribes in check. ",
            "keyString": "30299s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buddha",
            "optionA": "  rejected the theory of Karma ",
            "optionB": "  was non-committal on the theory of Karma ",
            "optionC": "  believed in the theory of Karma ",
            "optionD": "  suggested an alternative to the theory of Karma ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cycle of rebirth is determined by karma, literally \"action\". In the Buddhist tradition, karma refers to actions driven by intention (cetan\u0101), a deed done deliberately through body, speech or mind, which leads to future consequences. ",
            "keyString": "30312s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Buddhist literature consists of dialogues between the Buddha and his followers?",
            "optionA": "  Milnda Panha ",
            "optionB": "  Sutta Patika ",
            "optionC": "  Vinayapitaka ",
            "optionD": "  Buddhhacharita ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sutta Pitaka is the second of the three divisions of the Tripitaka or Pali Canon, the Pali collection of Buddhist writings of Theravada Buddhism. The Sutta Pitaka contains more than 10,000 suttas attributed to the Buddha or his close companions. ",
            "keyString": "30323s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a holy book of Jainism?",
            "optionA": "  Anga sahitya ",
            "optionB": "  Upang sahitya ",
            "optionC": "  Sutta pitaka ",
            "optionD": "  Kalpasutra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sutta Pitaka is the second of the three divisions of the Tripitaka or Pali Canon, the Pali collection of Buddhist writings of Theravada Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "69746s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following ruler was not contemporary to 'Buddha'?",
            "optionA": "  Udayin ",
            "optionB": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionC": "  Ajatshatru ",
            "optionD": "  Mahapadma Nanda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahapadma Nanda was the first ruler of Nanda Dynasty. He founded the dynasty in the year 424 BC and ruled for almost 62 years till 362 BC. He was not contemporary to Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "69778s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last in the succession of Jaina Tirthankaras was",
            "optionA": "  Parsvanatha ",
            "optionB": "  Rishabha ",
            "optionC": "  Mahavira ",
            "optionD": "  Manisubruta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahavira, also known as Vardham\u0101na, was the last and twenty-fourth tirthankara (ford-maker) who revived Jainism. In the Jain tradition, it is believed that Mahavira was born in the early part of the 6th century BC into a royal kshatriya family in present-day Bihar, India. ",
            "keyString": "69793s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For how many years Sumtinath Tirthankar prayed?",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  20 ",
            "optionC": "  30 ",
            "optionD": "  40 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSumtinath Tirthankar prayed 20 years. ",
            "keyString": "69805s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. The Ikshvaku rulers of southern India were antagonistic towards Buddhism.\nII. The Pala rulers of eastern India were patrons of Buddhism.\nWhich of these statement (s) is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I\u00a0and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pala rulers of eastern India were patrons of Buddhism. Dharmapala (ruled 8th century) was the second ruler of the Pala Empire of Bengal region in the Indian Subcontinent. He was the son and successor of Gopala, the founder of the Pala Dynasty. He greatly expanded the boundaries of the empire, and made the Palas a dominant power in the northern and eastern India. ",
            "keyString": "69817s15m21h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}